We have a lot of choices
to make about our diet.
Add to that, doing
the right thing
when it comes
to preventing
and treating a
chronic disease,
fighting a virus,
or losing weight,
and suddenly our
nutrition choices
can seem almost
overwhelming.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we conclude our two-part
series on fasting and cancer.
And we start with a story
about how the benefits
of short term fasting
translate in the
clinical setting.
The first randomized
prospective clinical evaluation
of the effects of fasting
on chemotherapy,
the incidence of
chemotherapy-induced nausea
and vomiting in cancer patients
was published in 2014,
but the patients were dogs.
Cancer-bearing dogs presenting
at a veterinary hospital were
randomized to be fasted for
24 hours before chemotherapy,
and those that were,
were significantly less likely
to suffer from vomiting
only 1 in 10 compared to 2
out of 3 in the non-fasted group,
which is great, but what can that
tell us about human medicine?
Evidently, not much.
It is nearly impossible to
rely on most animal data
to predict whether or not
an intervention will have
a favorable clinical benefit-risk
ratio in human subjects.
For example, mice have
a metabolic rate approximately
seven times higher
than humans,
so a single day of fasting can cut
lean body mass about 15%.
That would take over a
month of fasting in people.
So that dramatic study on mice
showing 100% alive versus
100% dead on high dose chemo
depending on whether
they were fasted for 60 hours,
what can that really tell us?
And when it comes to cancer,
rodents can bear
massive tumor loads,
whereas people generally
waste away and die
when tumor masses
reach just a thousandth
of our body weight.
You can't even necessarily
extrapolate from one rat to another
even within the same strain
bought from different dealers.
The only way to see
what happens in humans,
the only way to guarantee findings
are relevant is to study people.
The theory is that combining
fasting cycles with chemotherapy
could extend the survival of
advanced-stage cancer patients
by both retarding tumor progression
and reducing side effects,
or even providing an alternative
to chemotherapy altogether
in early-stage cancer patients,
but that's all contingent on it being
confirmed in human clinical trials.
First there were case series:
several patients diagnosed
with a variety of cancers
elected to undertake fasting
prior to chemotherapy
and shared their experiences.
Those who underwent chemo
both with and without fasting
reported a reduction of
fatigue, weakness, and
gastrointestinal side effects
while fasting; in fact felt better
across the board with zero
vomiting in the fasting group.
The weight lost during the few days
of fasting was rapidly recovered
in most of the patients and did
not lead to any detectable harm,
so overall was looking
feasible, safe,
with the potential to
ameliorate side effects.
But only randomized clinical
studies could tell for sure,
and so here we go.
Breast and ovarian cancer
patients fasting, starting 36 hours
before and ending 24 hours
after chemotherapy,
and it did appear to improve
the quality of life and fatigue,
but another study found
no such beneficial effects.
There did appear to perhaps
be less bone marrow toxicity
given the higher counts of red blood
cells and platelet-making cells,
but no benefit when it came
to killing off white blood cells --
the immune system cells --
so that was a disappointment.
Perhaps they didn't
fast long enough?
They only fasted 24 hours
before and after.
To find out the optimal duration,
20 cancer patients were split up
into three groups, fasting for
24, 48, or a total of 72 hours.
All those in the 24-hour group
suffered nausea after chemo,
but less than half
in the 72-hour group.
And most were vomiting
in the 24-hour group,
but none in the
longest fasting group.
Longer fasting groups also tended
to suffer less nerve damage
and less serious bone
marrow suppression.
Even after 24 hours of fasting,
two cycles of chemo can
knock people's white blood cells
down to sub-optimal levels, but
with 72 hours, chemo knocked their
immune system down but not out.
OK, so short-term fasting may reduce
chemotherapy-induced toxicity,
but what I want to know is
if it makes it work better?
A systematic review of 22 studies
found that overall fasting
was found to not only reduce
chemotherapy side effects, like
organ damage, immune suppression,
and chemotherapy-induced death,
but also to suppress tumor
progression, including
tumor growth and metastasis,
resulting in improved survival, but...
nearly all of the studies
were done on lab animals.
The studies on humans are
limited to evaluating safety
and side effects.
The tumor-
suppression effects of fasting --
for example, its influence on tumor
growth, metastasis and prognosis --
have not been evaluated until now.
To be continued.
In our final story we ask,
how might we replicate the protective
effects of fasting with food?
Short-term food withdrawal during
chemotherapy may begin to solve
the long-standing problem
with most cancer treatments:
how to kill the tumor
without killing the patient?
Short-term fasting --
for example,
for 48 hours before chemo
and 24 hours afterwards --
may reduce side effects, reduce
chemotherapy-induced toxicity.
However, the potential tumor-
suppressing effects of fasting --
for example, its influence on tumor
growth, metastasis and prognosis --
have not been evaluated until now.
No, actually, sadly, they mean
"have not been evaluated until now,"
meaning they have not
been evaluated yet, period.
So in answering the question to fast
or not to fast before chemotherapy,
it should be emphasized
that the evidence provided
by human studies
is still very limited.
Some argue that reducing
the side effects alone
could improve efficacy,
since patients could
withstand higher doses.
For example, the heart and
kidney damage associated
with the widely prescribed
anti-cancer drugs limit
their full therapeutic potential.
It's not clear, though, that
maximizing the tolerated
chemo dose would achieve
longer survival or
better quality of life.
For now, I think we should
just be satisfied with
the fewer side effects for
fewer side effects' sake.
Some cancer docs urge caution,
concerned about malnutrition.
That concern is echoed
in official guidelines
on nutrition in cancer patients.
Because of the risks
of malnutrition and,
yeah, maybe a day
or two might not hurt,
but because patients might
be tempted to prolong fasting
episodes without firm evidence
of a benefit, they feel
fasting during chemotherapy
cannot be recommended.
Fasting proponents agree that
patients with severe weight loss,
muscle wasting or malnutrition --
probably not good candidates
for even short-term fasting.
But out of the hundreds of
patients that have been tracked,
there's no evidence of severe adverse
events in terms of malnutrition
or weight loss with short-term
fasting or fasting-mimicking diets.
And those patients who did
experience a weight loss
during fasting typically
recovered their weight
before the subsequent cycle
of chemo without detectable harm.
But look, even if there is a risk,
we're talking about cancer here.
Accepting trade-offs is kind
of the name of the game.
People are willing to put up
with the risk of severe,
even life-threatening side
effects all the time.
And even if it just helped
alleviate some of the side effects,
it might be worth a try.
Of course, meanwhile Big Pharma
is busy trying to come up with drugs
aimed at reproducing the
beneficial effects of fasting.
Although fasting mimicking drugs
may be preferred by patients
who would rather pop a pill
than go without eating,
it will be years before
they'll ever be on the market,
and it's hard to imagine drugs
will be developed that are
both as effective and
as safe as fasting.
So is there anything
we can tweak in our diet
to get similar benefits
without having to fast?
The way fasting works
is by reducing levels
of a cancer-promoting
growth hormone known as
insulin-like growth factor 1.
It's the reduced levels
of IGF-1 that mediate
the differential protection
of normal and cancer cells
in response to fasting
and improves chemo's
ability to kill cancer
but spare normal cells.
How do we know this?
Because restoration of IGF-1
was sufficient to reverse
the protective effect of fasting.
Check it out.
Here's the growth of two cancer cell
lines, breast cancer and melanoma,
in a petri dish after being
exposed to chemotherapy.
Survival rates dropped down
into the 60s or even 20s.
But the same dose in starved
cells works even better.
Same dose, same starvation,
but drip back a little IGF-1
and the starvation benefit vanishes.
So reducing IGF-1 signaling
may provide the dual benefits
by protecting normal cells while
reducing tumor progression
and may even help prevent
the cancer in the first place.
As I explained before in my
"How Not To Die from Cancer" video,
and an important video
about animal protein --
which kind of gives away
the punch line --
but fasting isn't the only way
to drop IGF-1 levels.
Yes, a few days of fasting
can cut levels in half,
but that's largely because
you're cutting your protein intake.
Protein is a key determinant of
circulating IGF-1 levels in humans,
suggesting that reduced
protein intake may become
an important component
of anticancer and anti-aging
dietary interventions, particularly
a reduction in animal protein.
If you compare those eating strictly
plant-based diets, getting about the
recommended daily intake of protein,
0.8 grams per kg of body weight,
and compare them to people just
as slender but eating more typical
American protein intake, going
on a calorie-restricted diet
may lower IGF-1 a little, but eating
a plant-based diet can lower it more.
So not only may a diet centered
around whole plant foods
down-regulate IGF-1 activity,
potentially slowing the aging process,
but may be a way of turning
anti-aging genes against cancer.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
Or go to your local public
library for that matter.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.